"The Effects of Cleaning Products and
Air Fresheners on Lung Function"
In a recent review of the “Damaging
effects of household cleaning
products on the lungs”, researchers
noted that the “[a]dverse
respiratory effects of cleaning
products were first observed
in populations experiencing high level[s]
of exposure at the workplace,
such as cleaners and
health-care workers,
with a primary focus on asthma.”
But the occupational use of
disinfectants has also been linked
to a higher risk of developing
chronic obstructive pulmonary
diseases like emphysema.
And now we know it’s not just
workplace exposures but also
“common household exposures”
that are “risk factor[s] for
respiratory disorders in
childhood”, as well potentially
an important risk factor for
adult asthma, with common
household cleaning spray use
accounting for as many as
one in seven adult asthma cases.
The thought is that the inhalation
of chemical irritants may cause
injury of the airways that leads to
oxidative stress and inflammation.
Okay, so what can we do about it?
Well, it may indeed be limited to sprays.
Cleaning products not applied in
spray form were not associated
with asthma, and it’s possible
that environmentally friendly
cleaning products may
represent a safer alternative,
though they may still present some risk.
Ideally, safer cleaning products
should be available.
Unfortunately, the research suggesting
harm “has seldom been heeded
by manufactures, vendors, and
commercial cleaning companies.”
I wonder how much of that is
because “most of the workers
exposed to cleaning product
[both occupationally
and presumably domestically,]
are women.
One of the problems may be
the fragrance chemicals.
One in three Americans surveyed
“reported health problems
such as migraine headaches
and respiratory difficulties,
when exposed to fragranced products.”
And in about half it was so bad
they actually lost work over it.
“Results from this study reveal
that more than one third
of Americans suffer adverse
health effects, such as
respiratory difficulties
and migraine headaches,
from exposure to fragranced products.
Of [all] individuals, half reported
that the effects can be disabling.
Yet [more than] 99 percent
of Americans are exposed
to fragranced products at
least once a week . . .”
The effect on asthmatics
may be even worse,
affecting closer to two-thirds.
One compound that may be
of particular concern is
called 1, 4-dichlorobenzene,
also known as para-dichlorobenzene,
which is found in many
air fresheners, toilet bowl
deodorants, and mothballs.
It breaks down in the body into a
compound called 2,5-dichlorophenol,
which you pee out, giving
researchers a reliable measure
of your dichlorobenzene exposure.
Not only may it make respiratory
problems worse for those already
suffering from compromised airways,
but exposure to dichlorobenzene
“at blood levels found in
the general U.S. population,
may result in reduced [lung] function”
in people who start out
with normal breathing. What’s worse,
higher exposure was associated
with greater prevalence of
cardiovascular disease and cancer.
That’s not good!
So, better read the labels, right?
Surprisingly, there is “no law
in the U.S. [that] requires
the disclosure of all ingredients
in fragranced consumer products”.
In fact, for air fresheners, laundry
supplies, and cleaning products
they don’t even need to say
it has fragrance at all.
You don’t know until you smell it.
So, if you can’t tell which
products have which chemicals,
you can follow the lead of the CDC,
the Centers for Disease
Control and Prevention.
Not only is cigarette smoking
indoors prohibited at all times,
“[s]cented or fragranced products
are [also] prohibited at all times
in all interior space owned,
rented, or leased by CDC.”
I wish rideshare services
like Uber and Lyft would have
a similar policy or at least
a fragrance-free option.
About one in five or more than
a thousand Americans surveyed
said they would turn right
around and leave a business
if they smelled air fresheners
or some fragranced product,
so it’s in business’s best
interest too, since “[more than]
50 percent of the population
would prefer that workplaces,
health care facilities, and [their
health care] professionals,
hotels, and airplanes
were fragrance-free.”